So now let's begin to explore HTML.
So after this presentation you'll be
able to build a simple web page and
also you'll appreciate
the use of an HTML editor.
Here's some of the HTML
elements we're gonna look at.
So, first thing is, HTML is defined by
a particular group of people called
the World Wide Web Consortium.
So there is a particular place on
the internet where you can go.
And you can see all
the information about HTML.
And I strongly recommend you
don't go there, all right,
unless you're kind of an expert.
You're really already
quite proficient in HTML.
All of that detail there, because there's
a lot of detail, is really too much.
It's not about learning,
it's about referring to the HTML standard.
So this might be useful later after
you build your HTML skills, but
right now I would suggest, don't go there.
So lets look at HTML.
HTML commands are called elements.
Each element has a start tag and
an end tag.
So this is the paragraph element.
There's the start of the paragraph.
There's the end of the paragraph.
And there's some text which I
haven't shown in the middle of
the paragraph, okay?
That's the usual structure, start,
end, something in the middle.
However, there are some exceptions
which we'll look at later.
So, let's begin to make a webpage.
This is the basic structure of a webpage.
You have to have DOCTYPE html at the top,
then you start your html element.
And down the bottom you
finish your html element.
And then you have a head section,
and then you have a body section.
Okay, so this head section is basically
some kinds of information which
you don't see on the web page.
The body section is more things that
you actually see on the web page.
So, our first web page.
There's the complete source code.
We've done the things that we
saw on the last slide, and
we've added a few extra things.
A couple of extra things
in the head section.
A couple of extra things in
the body section as well.
This is what it looks like.
My web page.
Web page is awesome.
Very simple.
That is the .
That is the P that we saw, paragraph.
So we saw , the top thing and
we saw P, the paragraph.
So  is heading 1.
Again, start tag, end tags,
some text in the middle.
Basic structure of most HTML elements.
And also paragraph,
start paragraph, end paragraph, and
then some text in the middle.
Basic commands that you'll
see on many web pages.
Now, let's look, for a few slides,
let's look at the head part.
The stuff that we just talked about,
, and paragraph, was in the body part.
What about the head part?
So, basically, anything in the head
part is information about the webpage.
Usually you don't actually see
those things in the webpage.
So I had two things in my simple
demonstration webpage and
one was title and meta tag.
Obvious what they do.Title tells the
browser what the title is of the webpage.
And the meta tag, obviously,
tells the browser the author.
So, pretty simple, high level information
about the web page goes in the head part.
Other things you might
find in the head part.
You might see style instruction.
We'll talk about style a bit later.
You might see a link to a style sheet,
which is a separate file
containing style information.
You might see other types
of meta information.
Maybe description, key words,
maybe character set.
Lots of different type of meta information
you might see in a web page head section.
Other things you might see,
a piece of JavaScript code.
That might be in the head.
A link to a file which
has JavaScript code.
JavaScript, we talk about that later.
Okay.
You might see a base instruction and
that's basically saying you have
a website, a whole group of web pages.
Where are they going?
Where do they belong?
And it tells the browser
where they belong.
So, quite a lot of things that you
might see in the head section.
So, we've got lots of elements in HTML.
And some of them have attributes,
parameters, if you like.
So there's one attribute,
another attribute for the meta element.
So you can use speech marks,
double speech marks if you like.
And there's double speech marks.
But also, if you want,
you can use single speech marks.
Both of them are fine.
The browser doesn't
care which one you use.
So, let's begin to learn HTML a bit more.
Different ways of learning.
One way is to look at the source
code of any web page.
So here's an example, Wikipedia web page.
A website which has lots
of general information,
encyclopedia information about
millions of things around the world.
Go to that in your web browser and hit the
keyboard shortcut such as CTRL+U on a PC.
Or some other shortcuts on a Mac.
And you will see the source code.
And perhaps we'll have a quick
look at that right now.
So for example,
this is the website for Wikipedia.
I'd like to learn the HTML
from this website.
So I'm going to go over to my computer and
do CTRL+U because this is a PC and
just have a quick look at the HTML code.
All right.
This is the source code for
the Wikipedia website.
I can see things I already know about.
DOCTYPE html, start html, the head
section begins, meta tags, titles.
All of these things,
a lot of them I know already.
Even though, I just began to look at html.
But some things I don't know.
We can't cover everything
in this series of videos.
For example,
html it can have a language attribute.
This particular webpage
is in English language.
Okay, we don't have time to look
at all of these attributes.
You can learn them by
looking at websites and
looking at the source code
of different websites.
So here's a header section, if I keep
going down I'll see the body section.
I can learn a lot of things by
looking at this kinda website.
Okay, another way to learn HTML is
to look at different HTML editors.
All right, there's hundreds of editors.
Many, many to a quick google search and
you'll find a big, long list.
So they give you a nice, GUI environment,
a nice graphical user interface.
So that you can build HTML and you can
also see the source code that they create.
So these editors,
they're useful sometimes, especially
useful for complementing learning.
That's not replacing learning, but
complementing your learning of HTML.
Let's look at an example.
So here's an HTML editor,
this one is called TinyMCE.
And it actually works inside a webpage,
because this is actually a webpage.
And so let's do a quick example.
I'm gonna type some text here
in my little GUI environment.
And then I'm gonna apply some formatting.
I'm gonna apply the  format.
All right.
So, I'm gonna type some text,
it's going to be very small.
You won't see it very clearly.
And I'm gonna add the  style.
And then you'll see it and it a little bit
bigger and we can see the source code.
So, let's do some typing.
This is my webpage, something like that,
extremely small you can't really see it.
Let's select it and then apply a format.
And we're talking about the  format.
And yes,
now we can see that we have a large
size of text that is
using the head  tag.
Now what about my source code?
I wanna look at the code
created by the editor.
So I can copy it,
paste it into my own system.
So let's have a look at the source code.
And I can access that with
this particular menu.
So let's click and
look at the source code.
And make it a bit larger so
you can see it.
And there is my source code.
Fantastic, I didn't
have to type it myself.
This is my web page..
And I could copy that,
put it in my own web page,
put it in my own web system if I like.
Of course it's not just the simple things.
Like, .
There's a hundred different things
you could do with editors and
they'll construct the source code and
then you copy it and paste it.
Does it replace learning?
No, it doesn't really replace learning.
You still have to understand
everything it generates, okay?
So that's the end of our
first discussion about HTML.