Let's look at some advanced uses
of functions in JavaScript.
So, these are the different
things we're gonna look at.
How to assign a function to a variable.
How to pass a function to a function.
And also how to return
a function from a function.
Fairly advanced features.
And these are the different pieces
of code we're gonna look at.
So what we know so far is,
this is a typical way to make a function.
No problem at all, everything works fine.
Function, name of the function,
have some code inside it.
No problem, that's very typical.
You could also do one of these.
You can actually say, make a function but
you assign it to a variable name, okay?
Make a function as usual,
assign it to a variable.
If you like, you could actually have
the name of the function as well,
but you don't have to, this one hasn't
even written the name of a function.
But you could write the name if you like.
That function is assigned
to this variable and
you write all your code as
usual inside the braces.
So, you could do that.
We're giving a function to a variable and
that function is
declared when the browser gets
to this point in the code.
It may not get to this point at the start,
when the webpage is loaded.
It may get to this point, like for
example, it may run a function
with this inside it, later, possibly five
minutes after the webpage each has loaded.
That a difference to this one here.
This one is created when
the webpage is loaded.
These are ways to make a function
which are not straight away when
the webpage is loaded but
it could be later.
So there is some subtle differences.
Okay, what else could we do?
We could pass a function to a function.
In JavaScript,
a function is just an object and
you can pass that to a function.
Let's see an example.
So the idea of this is,
to check a operation.
So here's one line of code.
Result is myDivide and then we
are passing a function check, okay?
That is passed to the division.
It's just an example of passing
a function here to a function.
Now the general idea of this is,
if you divide a number by 0zero,
you'll get an error, okay?
You cannot divide a number by 0.
Any number.
So the simple idea here is,
we write a function but
we also include a checking function.
We pass the checking
function to that function.
And then it uses that checking function
to check if we can do a division.
And we can do a division if
the second number is not 0.
All right, so
that function is actually here, check.
All it does is, it simply checks if the
second number is not 0 then return true.
We can do division,
otherwise return false.
So there's a function.
We are passing that function,
check, goes to this function and
we've given it a different name, fn.
And so
now we can use that function, give it two
numbers which is the same two numbers.
Can we do 44 divide by 1,
let's try that out,
44 divide by 1 and that is given to
the checking function, which returns true.
So we get a message, it's okay,
we can divide 44 by 1 no problem at all.
And so we get the answer coming
back from my division, okay?
Otherwise, that checking
function has said,
not okay, we have a problem,
the second number is 0.
Okay, now it's a bit of a kind of
unusual example, a bit weird, but
it's just illustrating a real example
passing a function to another function and
then using that function.
All right, what else can we do?
We could return a function
from a function.
All right, so
let's look at an example of that.
So here's our main code and we've said
there's our function called counter.
And we could go and we could run that
function here and it does something and
it returns, it doesn't return a number,
it doesn't return text,
a string, it returns a function,
right there.
That function comes back and
is stored in the variable count, okay?
So we ran a function up here,
what did it do?
Nothing very clever, but
it returned a function in the variable.
All right, now we could use
the name of that variable and
we could run that function once,
twice, three times, and
each time we just add a number,
and it will show a 1, 2, 3, okay?
So, that is an example of
a function being returned
from a function and then being used.
Let's run this example.
There we are.
We get 1 and then 2, that's
the second time we ran the function,
which is stored in the variable.
And then 3, that's the third time we ran
the function stored in the variable.
And then we finished.
That's the end of our quick
discussion of some advanced
things you could do with
functions in JavaScript.