Let's look at element grouping in HTML.
So basically, this is just very simple
presentation talking about how to group
elements together into useful groups.
Two elements we're gonna look at,
fieldset and legend.
So the idea is nothing too complicated,
but it's simply to put
items that work together in a similar
structure in the same structure.
There's two ways to think about this.
One is the visual output on the webpage,
and then the other is the code.
So, the code,
you might want to group things together.
And the way to do that is to use
fieldset together with legend, and
when you look at your code,
you can realize, oh,
yes, I understand, these inputs
are related to personal information.
So it helps you as a programmer.
But also, there's a visual result,
which helps group this together as well.
So there's a visual side,
there's also a kind of programming side,
advantages to using fieldset and legend.
So, here, I've got my fieldset,
I've got my legend.
Personal information, two inputs.
What about here?
Another grouping, fieldset,
legend, Favorite things, okay?
So I've got two groups which
work together, all right?
What does it look like?
It looks like this.
So there's fieldset and
there's the legend.
This is fieldset has resulted
in the browser adding a box
around those things,
which are put together in the fieldset.
Okay, so I had a couple of things.
They're put together.
There's another couple of things.
It's a nice visual identity,
as well as, in the HTML,
a nice kind of coding identity as well,
grouping things together.
So that looks good.
This example is using a form.
But it doesn't have to be a form.
So, let's have a look at an example
which has nothing to do with forms.
This is just some kind of text
output in the web page, right?
A couple of things here.
I want it to be shown with a nice box
around it and a nice title at the top.
Nothing to do with forms.
Okay, I use the same code, and we get
a nice little summary, perhaps this is for
a game that you're building,
something like that.
Enemies, friends, this doesn't
have to take up the whole page.
It could be over on the left hand side.
Or on the right hand side.
Maybe the bottom, the top,
you could put it in a div and
put the div at any location,
as we talked about it another video.
So it's a nice visual way
to group elements together.