Let's now look at handling audio sound,
in a web page.
That's the whole target of this video.
It's just about sound.
We need to use the audio element and
several attributes.
So, how can we get sound into a web page?
Well basically, audio, and then src, and
then the name of the file,
and then /audio.
Okay that's it, that will bring
in a sound into the web page.
What's the problem with this example?
Well you can't hear anything.
It'll bring a sound into the web page.
It's in memory, but it won't play it.
So how do we play it?
All right,
we have to add a little bit more.
We have to add another attribute,
autoplay.
So as soon as the web page loads,
it will load the sound file and
then it will play the sound
file straight away.
So let's check that by running
this example over here.
[MUSIC]
Works fine.
Okay, I'll stop it now and
then we'll carry on.
[MUSIC]
Okay, so.
Oops, let's forget this little thing here.
So, basically that was the autoplay.
Basically we told the browser,
bring in a sound file and
then immediately start playing it as
soon as the sound file has loaded.
All right, what else could we do?
Well, I have no control
over the sound file so far.
I can't restart it or anything like that.
No problem, all the modern
browsers have audio controls.
All right, so that's another attribute.
Bring in the sound file.
Show the user some controls so
they can play and rewind and
fast forward and change volume, the sound.
Okay, so that example is here,
it should work if I try it right here.
[MUSIC]
Yep no problem at all.
This is provided by the browser okay?
That is the controls.
I could jump around, jump to the end,
change the volume, all of those things.
Simple stuff, but I'm just gonna stop it
right now and move on to the next example.
Okay what else can we do?
We can loop things.
Okay we can loop things.
Why is that useful?
For example, maybe you have a game and
it's got some background music.
And you only have two minutes
of your background music.
But the game goes on for ten minutes.
Okay.
Then you have your game system like this.
You say start the system,
start the audio and keep looping it.
Every two minutes it will start it again,
again, again,
if the sound is two minutes long, okay?
So keep repeating.
Might be useful.
We have a simple example here.
[MUSIC]
Loop.
Loop, and its gonna loop and loop and
loop for infinity until I stop it.
[MUSIC]
All right, that was simply
the loop attribute right there.
Full screen okay let's carry on.
What about older browsers?
Cuz those kind of things
we just looked at,
they were really for most recent browsers.
And sometimes some people don't
quite have the most recent browsers.
Maybe they're using a mobile phone
which is a few years out of date.
It cannot be updated, things like that.
So, It's wise to do some
things kind of specially.
One sensible approach is
to use MP3 format sound.
It's supposed to work in all browsers.
It works pretty good on PCs and
Macs but in the mobile environment,
it does cause some problems still.
But still, that is a good target
to start with, MP3 format.
And how can you handle these older
browsers a bit more professionally?
So for example,
instead of it just not working,
you can actually get those older browsers
to actually show a little message.
And the way you do it is like this.
This could be sound or audio,
it could be actually any HTML tag.
So you have this tag, whatever the tag
is that you're trying to get working.
But you know it won't work
on some older systems.
So you write the name of the tag and
that will work for the newer systems.
For the older systems, they will ignore
that tag because they don't understand it,
because they're like
three years out of date.
So they ignore this and they ignore this.
But they do pick up a simple
paragraph in the middle.
So older browsers, not very good browsers,
not very complete,
they'll pick up the middle.
But the newer browsers
will ignore the middle and
they'll just use the start and end.
So, that's how you handle older browsers.
Nothing to do with sound by itself,
but actually it's a general method.
All right, let's move on.
There's an example.
So there's sound, and then for
older browsers, or not very good browsers,
not very complete browsers,
there's a message.
That message will not be
shown in the newer browsers.