All right, let's look at handling file
upload from the form point of view.
So basically, it's enough skills
after this presentation so
that you can actually handle some
kind of file upload system, but
we don't really look at
the server side of things.
So, this is all related to one particular
attribute, file type, input type is file.
So, there's actually two sides when
you want to build a system which will
upload a file and
then send it to a server program,
and then the server program
has a copy of the file.
Of course, you have to handle
the form side of things, usually, and
also the server side,
program side of things.
Now, this presentation is pretty quick.
We're just focused on the form side of
things rather than the server side.
So, let's have a look
at a basic structure.
We know that we have form,
we know that we have some kind of action,
some kind of method.
Something we haven't seen before,
encode type.
That tells the browser when
we send the file to attach,
let's use the word attach,
to attach the file, or
files, that you want to upload to
the message which goes to the server.
All right?
So that's essential if you're doing file
upload, all right?
If you're not doing file upload,
you can kind of forget about it.
The other thing is this, method is post.
Well, we had a brief
discussion of that before.
If you're doing big things like files,
absolutely essential you
use the post method.
Use the get method, it totally won't work.
Use the post method and
it should work, okay?
So that's some extra things
you have to think about.
You also have to do this
kind of thing here.
This gives you a file selector.
So the user sees the form,
sees the file selector, click on it,
select the file in the hard disk, and
then press submit button,
off goes the file to the server program.
Here's a real world example where
I've filled in the parameters.
So yes, post method, and
there's an exact URL.
And the other stuff is
pretty much the same.
Some kind of submit button,
some kind of file selector button, okay?
So that's a real world example.
I won't do it right now.
The reason is, I haven't actually handled
the server program in this example,
simple example.
To discuss that in detail
is another presentation.
So, we're not gonna discuss
the server program in detail now.
On the form side of things, the HTML,
this is what it looks like.
This was my file selector.
This is the submit button, of course.
And that's all we need, right?
Do those have the parameters
correct in the form at the top and
then you press Upload and
the file will go over to the server.
What does the server do?
Well, the server, program on the server,
as we briefly mentioned before,
it could do a million things.
For files,
it may have some extra things to do.
The server program has access
to the file sent by the browser.
But it may have to, for example,
move the file to another directory.
It may have to change
the permissions of the file.
It may have to do quite a lot of different
things, save the file in a database.
It totally depends on the system
that you're building, okay?
But in this presentation,
we're just focused on the HTML
part of handling file upload.