Okay, let's have some more
discussion about style.
So basically, after this presentation,
you'll understand inline style, and
pseudo-classes, and
also a little bit about which rule
has more priority than other rules.
These are the pseudo-classes
we're gonna look at.
So, first thing, inline style.
So, inline style is
when you type the style
that you want to apply right there for
that particular element.
So for
this particular paragraph we want to say
all the text will be on
the right hand side.
That's what we're saying right there.
So that is inline style.
So that's very different to
what we've talked about before.
Before, we talked about putting
style at the top of a page,
and this is really the opposite.
This is saying, no, I don't wanna
put it on the top of the page.
I wanna put it right here for one
particular element right there, all right?
So it's harder to manage, because you
have to go through all the code, and
try to work out which
inline style is being used,
if everything is not at
the top in the style section.
So it can be a bit more troublesome.
Here's an example.
This has a list, unordered list.
And we have four list items in the list.
And we have a style rule at the top,
which says every list item is
gonna have a yellow background.
Okay.
No problem.
Four list items,
they will all have a yellow background.
However, down here, we said, no,
I want to apply this inline
style to the third list item.
So, because we've said this,
this is a higher priority than this.
So this one will indeed be in purple and
all the others will be in yellow.
So we get a result like this.
Yellow, yellow, yellow, but then we said
inline style for the third list item, so
it's purple.
It has a higher priority.
All right.
Let's talk about another thing.
Context control for style rules.
You could have a rule
which looks like this.
And it says all right, list items,
those will be red color.
But what it actually says is list items
which are within an unordered list,
those list items, no other list items,
will be red, all right?
So, list item inside unordered list, red.
Any other list item will not be red.
So here's an example piece of code.
We've got a list and another list.
This one is an unordered list,
this one is an ordered list.
And then we've said up here, a rule.
So we've said list items
in the unordered list,
that's the first list,
they will be yellow.
Now, that will not apply
to the second list.
So here's the result.
You can see the style rule has not
been applied to the second list, but
it got applied to the first list.
Let's look at another subject,
pseudo-classes.
So, pseudo-classes are basically
classes with, what I tend to say is,
some kind of intelligence,
some kind of extra capability.
So here's the first one, and it is hover.
So it's saying when the user
puts their mouse over heading 1,
it will change to red.
So, put your mouse over heading 1,
the color of the text will become red.
Move your mouse away from the heading 1,
it will go back to the previous color.
So that's hover, so it's some kind
of intelligence, if you like.
Now, there's a lot of these
pseudo-classes, many, many, of them.
So let's just have
a look at a few of them.
So for example, here, if you have a link,
then that will be a red color, all right?
Now that applies to a, because actually,
that's what a link is.
So it has to be a.
Remember a, anchor.
So, any link will be red color.
What about here?
visited.
That means that the person who is using
the browser, if they have visited
a link and the link is shown on
the webpage, then you can fix up a color.
So again, that has to be for
a, because a is for links.
So anything that you have visited
will be shown in red color.
active.
So, active means you
are currently following the link.
You're currently following the link.
Now that could be just
like 0.1 of a second.
You've clicked on a link, and
the browser is just going and
grabbing the next webpage and
building it, and then it displays
the link, it could be very, very quick.
Even though it's very quick, there is
a pseudo-class for handling that, you're
currently following and grabbing the next
webpage, because you clicked on a link.
All right, it will apply this style.
And again, that has to be for
a, cuz it's all about links.
What about this one?
Well, this one doesn't have to be for a.
This is pretty straightforward.
This is any element which is empty.
It has nothing inside it.
All right, it could be every
paragraph which is empty.
It will use this style rule.
So this is just five of them, but
there's actually another, 20, 30, 40,
a lot more pseudo-classes.
So here's an example.
And we've set up these rules that we
just looked at, the pseudo-classes,
and we built a simple
webpage to explore them.
And then it looks like this, and so
we can try some of these out, but
some of them, remember,
are quite hard to see.
So let's go for the hardest one first.
Remember, the hardest
one is the active link.
Okay, that is the link that
is currently being processed.
It may be hard to see.
Purple.
So, active link, it will become purple.
So let's try to open the example, and
then we'll play with it and try these out.
Active link will become purple
is the first one we'll try.
So here's the example,
let's try that first one.
Active link should become purple, but you
may have to be very quick with your eyes,
but let's try it.
There's four links here and a list,
a series of lists here,
one single list with lots of list items.
So let's try the active link.
So I'm gonna click on this one, and yes,
it managed to show that in
the correct style very quickly.
Okay, so that was active link.
What else did we have?
We had a link which has not yet
been activated.
You can see there's some yellow
color being applied behind it.
And what about if we
have visited the link?
Well, now we have visited the link, so
it's using that style rule as well.
Down here we have empty
style rule being used.
All right, so this particular
list item had nothing inside it,
so that triggered the use
of that particular style.
And then the other thing we used
was hover, so let's show hover.
So you can see if I put my mouse over
these, they change the background color.
Okay, a little bit hard to demonstrate
some pseudo-classes because they
have some kind of intelligence,
if you like.
But yes, you can see mouseover has
triggered the different style.
So that's our brief introduction to
three different areas of styles,
including this one,
which is pseudo-classes.