Let's have a look at
Timer Events in JavaScript.
That's what we're gonna focus on.
So these are the commands
we're gonna look at.
In general, the idea is simple, it's doing
something later, possibly many times.
That's the general idea.
So we call that timers.
Very, very useful for
dynamic web page behavior.
So how do we construct
a timer in JavaScript?
We make a variable and then we use
the variable to point to a timer.
All right.
We just set up a timer, and
then that timer is going to run
some JavaScript code,
such as a function, a little bit later.
So this part here is setting
up something to happen later.
What's gonna happen?
This function is gonna be executed.
When is it gonna happen?
It's gonna happen 1,000 later.
Now that is a value in a milliseconds,
so it is actually 1 second,
1,000 is 1 second.
So one second later this
function will be executed.
Now when it does this, it doesn't wait.
You can do other things with
your JavaScript code, many,
many different things.
And then suddenly, one second later,
that code will be executed.
So that's the idea, doing something
a little bit later in time.
So here's an example,
let's run this example.
Here it is, how long do you want to sleep?
All right, so we can type in
a value such as perhaps 8,000.
Something like that, and then press OK.
And remember, we're gonna use that
value to set the delay for a timer.
So we do OK, nothing happens.
Don't see anything happening.
But we have set up a timer, and eight
seconds later, boom, up comes a message.
Wake up, wake up, wake up, wake up.
It's a silly example, but
it just shows the idea of a delay before
that JavaScript function is executed.
Okay, let's go back to our presentation.
So that was simple to
let's have a look at that.
There's our web page, when we loaded
our webpage we ran some code,
what does the code do?
It sets things up, all right.
Functions can have any name this
is just a kinda silly name.
And so what does that do?
Well it shows the question,
how long do you want to sleep?
And then we put whatever
that person types.
We're using prompt, so
they can type something.
Whatever they type gets
stored in a variable.
And then we use that variable for
the duration of a timer.
In other words,
we say after that many milliseconds,
we're gonna run this function here.
Where is this function?
This function is down here.
Very simple,
it just makes a little window, "WAKE UP!
WAKE UP!
WAKE UP!!", very simple little example.
There's the key part where we do a delay,
and
we run that function after the number
which is entered by the user.
Right, let's carry on.
Let's do a kind of more advanced example,
if you like.
Now, let's show this one first.
So, here's the example.
As you can see, there is a picture.
That picture is moving over to the right.
How do we control the speed?
Well, that's controlled with a timer.
So, let's have a look at the code,
which makes this work.
So, when we load that web page,
what do we see?
Well, there's our web page.
And we see basically a picture, an image.
That is the image of the stones.
And we apply some style rules so that our
JavaScript code can move the position.
Used by adding position absolute and
reset the left position.
That's the one that we change
with out JavaScript code.
So that sets things up.
When the web page is loaded, start
the timer and it runs this function here.
What does it do?
It finds in memory, it finds that picture.
Both the stones using get element by ID.
And then it updates a variable which
is storing the X position of the image.
There's the variable here.
Start with the value zero and
then every time this function is executed
we increase it by one and
what do we do with that?
Well, we use that variable,
x position, we use it and
we put it in the left property, right?
The left attribute, in other words,
the x position of the image.
We find the image and
then we change the style dot left,
the x position of the image, so
that will update it at the new position,
which is moved a little
bit over to the right.
Now, what do we finally,
down here, the last line of code?
Well, we set up a timer, and
that timer is for the next time.
Because we want to
continually move that image.
We set up a timer,
after a very small piece of time,
one 20th of a second I think.
After one 20th of a second,
it will run the same function again.
Right, set timer.
This is inside set timer.
It is running the same function again,
a little bit later.
All right, so a little bit later,
run this function again, and
then it will increase the x.
It will update the x_position of
the image, and it will run itself again,
increase x, update position, again, again,
and we have a special kind of timer loop.
So, that's what we saw when
we just run the example.
Okay.
So let's say you wanna stop
that movement because that movement
goes on forever unless you stop it.
Maybe you wanna stop that movement.
Stop a timer.
Well if you've started a timer
in the way that we showed.
You start a timeout and you just give
it a name to point to that timeout.
If you do that, then all you have
to do to stop that movement or
whatever you're doing you just say
clear timeout and then you use the name
that you used when you made
the timer in the first place, okay?
So we used the word timer, so we use the
word timer here and that will immediately
stop that loop process, it will stop the
timer Here's an example where we do that.
We add a button to stop that.
So, let's have a look.
Okay.
So, here is this example.
And you can see it's the same as before,
picture moving to the right hand side.
But I just added a button here and
that button, when I click on it,
it triggers an event and we run some code.
So, let's do it.
Let's press stop.
And now you can see, yeah,
the picture is not moving anymore.
I have in effect stopped the time
of process, I've stopped the timer.
Let's carry on with the presentation.
So here's our code and, as I said,
as we saw just now,
we've added a button, simple button.
Click on the button,
then it runs some code.
What does the code do?
It clears the timer.
And where do we get this ting from,
the_timer?
Well, that was the one that we used,
the variable name that we
used when we made the_timer.
So, as long as we use the same name,
then we can clearTimeout,
clear this particular timer.
Because you can have as many timers
as you'd like at the same time.
So that's adding a clear of the timer.
Let's carry on.
What else could we do?
Well, that works fine.
It's totally okay.
There is another alternative.
setInterval, and it's very, very similar.
How do we set it up?
Well, we just do setInterval.
That's different to setTimeout,
setInterval.
We run this code, and we've got a number.
So far,
it looks identical to set time out, but
the difference is after you've done this,
every 2 seconds, it will run this code.
Every 2 seconds.
Not just once.
Again and again and again and again, okay?
So the other question is,
how do we stop it?
Something's happening,
again and again and again.
How do we stop it?
Well we would use clear again,
clearInterval this time
because it's interval.
And again you clear that variable,
that variable that you used to start it.
Let's do a quick example,
let's have a look.
So here is our example it is
exactly the same as before,
the only difference it looks
the same as before but
the difference is in the coding we
have now used setinterval to trigger
the repeating pattern instead of
using settimeout every single time.
Let's have a look at the code.
So basically, we rewrote a previous
example, so that it used set time out.
So, we load the webpage, and let's look
at the code which is a bit different.
When the webpage has loaded,
we set up an interval.
We set up an interval.
Every 50 milliseconds we will run the code
and the code is the same as before.
It's responsible for
changing the x value + 1 and
then moving the image by that new x value.
Now, because we use setInterval that
automatically runs that function
every 50 milliseconds.
So up here in this function that we built,
I've removed the loop function right here.
I said here, before, set timeout so it
runs it again, set timeout, set timeout,
set timeout.
We don't need to do that anymore.
Because we've set up an interval,
it automatically does that repetition
process every 50 milliseconds.
Then the only thing that I changes also
was the button, kick on the button,
what does it do?
Clear interval instead of clear time out.
Okay, clear interval.
All right, apart from that
it's the same visual result,
it's just using interval and
clear interval instead of set time out.
You really have a choice
of which ones to use.
So that's the end of our discussion
about timers in JavaScript.